<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Juan Carlos Muñoz-Mora</title>
    <description>This is the personal web-page of Juan Carlos Muñoz Mora Ph.D. in Economics.
</description>
    <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jcmunozmora.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 19:08:13 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 19:08:13 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prevalence, Economic Contribution, and Determinants of Trees on Farms across Sub-Saharan Africa (2017). Forest Policy and Economics (in press). with Daniel C. Miller and Luc Christiaensen.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Prevalence, Economic Contribution, and Determinants of Trees on Farms across Sub-Saharan Africa (2017).” (2016). Forest Policy and Economics (in press). with Daniel C. Miller and Luc Christiaensen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees on farms are often overlooked in agricultural and natural resource research and policy in Sub-Saharan Africa. This article addresses this gap using data from the Living Standards Measurement Study-Integrated Surveys on Agriculture in five countries: Ethiopia, Malawi, Nigeria, Tanzania, and Uganda. Trees on farms are widespread. On average, almost a third of rural smallholders grow trees. They account for an average of 17% of total annual gross income for tree-growing households and 6% for all rural households. Gender, land and labor endowments, and especially forest proximity and national context are key determinants of on-farm tree adoption and management. These new, national-scale insights on the prevalence, economic contribution and determinants of trees on farms in Africa lay the basis for exploring the interaction of agriculture, on-farm tree cultivation, and forestry to gain a more complete picture of the dynamics of rural livelihoods across the continent and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1389934116304592&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-paper-older-version&quot;&gt;Working Paper (older Version)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.profor.info/sites/profor.info/files/publication/WPS7802.pdf&quot;&gt;World Bank&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;related-news&quot;&gt;Related News&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.profor.info/knowledge/it’s-not-just-forests-matter-africa-trees-farms-provide-substantial-benefits&quot;&gt;PROFOR Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;replications-files&quot;&gt;Replications files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://treesonfarm.github.io&quot;&gt;Replication Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/articles/2017/01/02/articule_treesonfarm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/articles/2017/01/02/articule_treesonfarm.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GIS for Applied Economics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this course, we introduce students to the basic tools to analyze, create and manipulate different types of datasets from Geographic Information Systems (GIS). The aim of the course is to provide students with a basic knowledge to master the spatial data analysis toolbox, which offers alternative solutions to a broad range of empirical problems of applied economics. It is a practical course in which students are required to have an active participation through practices during lectures and problem sets. We will explore the basic GIS Desktop tools (i.e. ArcGIS and QGIS) as well as some GIS applications in standard statistic packages (Stata and R). However, an especial emphasis will be placed on building standalone solution based on Python (e.g. GDAL, FIONA, among others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;course-homepage&quot;&gt;Course Homepage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gisforappliedeconomics.github.io&quot;&gt;Webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/teaching/2016/11/01/courses_gis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/teaching/2016/11/01/courses_gis.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>teaching</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Returning Home after Civil War - Food security, nutrition and poverty among Burundian households, with Philip Verwimp</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Returning Home after Civil War - Food security, nutrition and poverty among Burundian households” (2017). Journal of Development Studies (in press). with Philip Verwimp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civil wars often force people to leave their homes. Displaced populations run higher risk in terms of disease, hunger and death, something that is well-documented. They leave their land, cattle and other assets behind for an uncertain existence in a refugee camp or depend on relatives or friends. But what happens when they return back home? This paper investigates the food security and poverty of formerly displaced households. Using the 2006 Core Welfare Indicator Survey for Burundi we compare their food intake and their level of expenses with that of their non-displaced neighbours. We test whether it is the duration of displacement that matters for current welfare or the time lapsed since returning. We use log-linear and ordered probit models as well as propensity score matching and an IV-approach to control by self-selection bias. We find that the individuals and households who returned home just before the time of the survey are worse off compared to those who returned several years earlier. It takes 8 to 10 years after return before the level of welfare of the displaced converges to that of the non-displaced. The duration of displacement seems not to matter. On average, the formerly displaced have 11% lower food expenses but only 8% lower calorie intake, showing that the formerly displaced consume relatively more high calorie products. The formerly displaced also report more children with a smaller size at birth. Despite international, government and NGO assistance, the welfare of recent returnees is lagging seriously behind in comparison with the local non-displaced populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-papers-old-version&quot;&gt;Working Papers (old version)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideas.repec.org/p/hic/wpaper/123.html&quot;&gt;HiCN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;replications-files&quot;&gt;Replications files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon Request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Submission&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/articles/2015/04/02/articule_returnig_home.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/articles/2015/04/02/articule_returnig_home.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Violent Conflict and Land Tenure - Evidence of Strategic Expropriation from Colombia, with Lukas Kleine-Rueschkamp</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently working on a first draft&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_land_conflict.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_land_conflict.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fighting while Talking - Assessing the impact of civil war on agriculture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper analyzes the impact of an increase in the armed conflict on agricultural production using the case of the Colombian coffee sector. I exploit a natural experiment which caused the level of violence to vary significantly due to the unexpected rupture of the peace dialogues between the Colombian government and the FARC in 2002. Using data provided by the National Federation of Coffee Growers of Colombia, I estimate the Intention to Treat (ITT) using a Difference-in-Difference approach. Results suggest that an exogenous increase in the levels of violence induced a reduction of hectares allocated to coffee of -0.06 Ha on average. Moreover, on an average farm (2 ha of land allocated to coffee), an exogenous increase in  the levels of violence decreased the sowing of new coffee by 3.5%. This paper contributes to the literature on the microeconomics costs of conflict in agricultural production, providing further information on the mechanisms behind the effects (labor market).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-paper&quot;&gt;Working Paper&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available upon request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;replications-files&quot;&gt;Replications files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon Request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently working on a new version&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_figthing_coffee.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_figthing_coffee.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Civil War and Household Structure - evidence from Burundi , with Richard Akresh and Philip Verwimp  Verwimp.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper analyzes whether civil war modifies household structure by boosting individual migration. The identification strategy uses a unique two waves longitudinal data set from Burundi, for 1997 and 2008. This data set was collected during ongoing conflict and allows tracking individual migration decision over ten years. Besides the traditional conflict exposure measures at village level, our data gathered yearly information on household victimization. Results show that higher exposure to violence increases the probability to individual non-marital migration. These effects are concentrated on poor households and those household members that are adults or men. Our results are consistent with aggregated measure of conflict exposure, as well as household level victimization measures. Furthermore, we found that whereas marital migration in adult un-married women is unrelated with exposure to violence at village level, it does with household victimization approaches. In particular, we found that being victim of any assets related losses is related to an increase of marital migration for middle age unmarried women. It could imply the use of marriage market as strategy to face liquidity constraints.  Results are robust to including province–specific time trends, alternative conflict exposure measures, and different levels of aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-paper&quot;&gt;Working Paper&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available upon request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;replications-files&quot;&gt;Replications files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon Request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently working on a new version&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_migration_burundi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_migration_burundi.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lumière Project Report of the Baseline Survey, (2015) funded by UNICEF and ULB (coordinated by Philip Verwimp)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The project aims at introducing alternative sources of energy at the household level. The main rationale for that is the very low use of electricity in Burundi – most people are off the grid – and the disadvantages that come with the use of combustible energy sources such  as kerosene (cost, smell, danger, irritation, supply).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to inform the UNICEF-Burundi team about the need and demand for energy at the household level, the Université libre de Bruxelles (ULB) – as part of its ongoing Partnership  with UNICEF-Burundi – was asked to study the current use of energy at the household level,  prior to the start of the project. Such study would not only inform UNICEF-Burundi on  energy use, energy expenditures, demand for energy and willingness to pay, but would also  serve as a baseline study to test the impact of the project after its implementation. The baseline study thus forms part of an evaluation design in which the survey team has also  interviewed households in communities who will not be serviced by the project. The group  constitutes the control group to which project results will be compared. Such comparison is  at its best when the treatment and control groups have been selected randomly. This is the  case in the current design. We have 29 control communities (at the level of the sous-colline)  and 34 treatment communities. A total of 1000 households have been interviewed in the  baseline survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-report&quot;&gt;Final Report&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon Request&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_lumiere.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_lumiere.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>policy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Disentangling True from Self-Reported Attitude-Behavior Consistency - An Experiment on Survey Questionnaire, with Marco Giani and Philip Verwimp.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Quantifying the level of Attitude-Behavior consistency is one of the rationales behind the progressive incorporation of attitudinal questions in childcare-related survey questionnaires. We argue that the questionnaire design, and in particular the order and timing of questions on attitudes (attitudes toward a behavior) and practices (behavioral intentions), may entail different strength of cognitive dissonance, thereby biasing the estimated level of unobservable “true consistency” in an asymmetric way. In a Randomize Control Trial (RCT) we run in Burundi, a sample of household is randomly treated with four different KAP designs: (i) Questions on practices precede questions on attitudes within the same subsection (control group); (ii) Questions on attitudes precede questions on practices within the same subsection (control group. (Treatment I); (iii) Questions on practices precede questions on attitudes in different subsections (treatment II); and, (iv) Questions on attitudes precede questions on practices in different subsections (treatment III). The most important result is that behavioral self-reports predict attitudinal self-reports more than the opposite independently of the timing imposed by the questionnaire. Higher aggregate consonance induced by behavioral questions suggests that the strength of attitudes is relatively weak in the specific context of rural Burundi. We offer a cognitive-dissonance reduction based explanation, but low accessibility of the studied attitudes in the memory, low frequency at which they are evoked or low extent to which they are grounded in direct experience are also compatible with the described effect. Several alternative inference specifications are presented and encompass various level of aggregation. The implications for KAP survey design are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-paper&quot;&gt;Working Paper&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available upon request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;replications-files&quot;&gt;Replications files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon Request&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;status&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently working on a new version&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_kap_burundi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/in_progress/2015/04/02/progress_kap_burundi.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inequality in Education, School-dropout and Adolescent lives in Burundi, (2014) funded by UNICEF and ULB (coordinated by Philip Verwimp)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The report offers an in-depth, quantitative study of four themes that are important to UNICEF’s programs on peace building in the education sector. These are enrollment, drop-out, youth and violence as well as inequality. Each theme is discussed below. The quantitative approach is paralled with qualitative analysis from field visits, interviews and focus group discussions with pupils, teachers and school directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to analyse the education sector from a quantitative point of view we use several datasets that have been collected in Burundi between 2005 and 2012. These are the Multiple Cluster Indicator Surveys (MICS, waves 2 in 2000 and 3 in 2005), the Core Welfare Indicator Survey (QUIBB, 2006), the Enquete Prioritaire Household Survey (PS, 2007), and the Demographic and Health Survey (DHS, 2010). For having also a longer term perspective with data preceding the civil war, we also use the DHS (1987). These datasets are at the individual and household level and together they cover a large number of topics of interest for this report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the above surveys we also make use of administrative data sources. The Ministry of Primary Education collects a large amount of data on education that, to the best of our knowledge, are not used for policy guidance or policy preparation. This report will show how such official data can be used to study inequalities in the education sector and point to alternative policies to address the observed inequalities. In particular we will perform an analysis of the results of the Concours National, a nationwide exam , for which we have used the results of the 2010 exam. This will allow us to discuss regional and school-level variation in the quality of education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our qualitative field work was performed in 8 schools in the provinces of Cibitoke, Gitega and Makamba. These provinces were chosen in order to attain variation in terms of several variables that came out salient in our quantitative research as well as from discussions with UNICEF-Burundi staff. These were poverty, legacy of the civil war, presence of returnees and gender. Inside the province schools were selected randomly and interviews touched upon all issues, not only those who were believed to be particularly relevant for that province. Respondents were selected among the 5th and 6th graders in accordance with representativeness key (performing and not- performing students, girls and boys, different age groups (from 12 to 18, difference due to high repetition rates), members of ethnic minorities /if found/). Total: 54 students, 6 headmasters, 3 vice-directors, and 1 teacher were interviewed.
The report is prepared by a team from the Université libre de Bruxelles (ULB) in extensive cooperation with the staff of the UNICEF-Burundi office. It is one of the outputs of the ongoing Partnership between ULB and UNICEF-Burundi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-report&quot;&gt;Final Report&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://solvay.edu/sites/upload/files/clean_report_educ_final3.pdf&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_education_burundi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_education_burundi.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>policy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Uraba - abundance and dispute for land. An approach to the relationship between armed conflict and land property system (in Spanish (2011), funded by Universidad EAFIT and Gobernación de Antioquia (Co-cordinated with Jorge Giraldo)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-report&quot;&gt;Final Report&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://solvay.edu/sites/upload/files/clean_report_educ_final3.pdf&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_uraba.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jcmunozmora.github.io/policy/2015/04/02/policy_uraba.html</guid>
        
        <category>coffee</category>
        
        <category>development</category>
        
        
        <category>policy</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
